[Music]
[Applause]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio is brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine online at computer org
slash software this March 21st and 22nd
don't miss technique night in Burlingame
California just minutes from the San
Francisco Airport come to tech ignite to
get rock-solid info on forecasts on
adaptive cybersecurity emerging
technologies machine learning and deep
learning operational intelligence and
much more join tech superstars Steve
Wozniak and Grady Booch plus sea level
leaders from Netflix Google IBM
Salesforce GE digital and Intel to gain
valuable insights to learn about real
world solutions you can start applying
today register now for the I Triple E
computer society's premier conference
tech ignite at tech ignite computer org
and discover the truth behind technology
for software engineering radio this is
Robert bloomin today I'm joined by John
Al's paw
John is the CTO of Betsy where he was
previously the SVP of infrastructure and
operations for over 17 years he has
worked in system operations in the
biotech government and online media
industries he's the recipient of a
master's degree in human factors and
system safety at Lund University and is
the author of two books web operations
keeping the data on time and the art of
capacity planning John is a popular
conference speaker on reliability
availability and failure John welcome to
software engineering radio thanks for
having me John we've all seen headlines
about outages of very high profile
websites even businesses with huge
economic value and lots of resources
still experienced unwanted downtime I
have an article AWS suffers five-hour
outage in the u.s. from September 2015
and one from last year Gmail outage hits
the US and Europe I would like to talk
with you today about why in spite of our
objective to be up that system still
have downtime how we try to avoid that
and what we can learn from it like this
start with can we define what an outage
is well yeah that's a good question
what's a failure what's an outage I
think that these things are generally
constructed and so what one organization
might say is an outage might be
something different from another
organization in some cases it's just
entirely about the business so I mean
think about it some businesses are
entirely driven by native apps and their
web presence is really nothing but you
know some sort of maybe just like
introduction or brochure really just
sort of information so if the web site
goes down did you have an outage and so
I think how I'm just earlier this week
Delta had an outage
Delta Airlines had an outage and so I
think that it's I think it's contact
specific I think the most important part
is instead of like reaching for a I
guess a common definition of outage or
failure really I like to just refer them
to as untoward events and then that way
it's a little bit more I don't know
context specific but it might I mean in
general its I'm doing some business and
I can't do the business because of some
of the tools that I have that that I
need to run the business aren't
available or they don't work the way I
you know the people who are using them
expect them then it's a loss of the
service at the end user wants to get
from the system yeah but I could you
could you could probably say that yeah
I'm aware that a lot of planning goes
into dealing with predictable things
that can go wrong in a system what are
some of the predictable things that can
go wrong well I mean that's the that's
the funny thing
so most outages especially the ones that
you hear about our businesses of that
are notable right so the reason why
they're notable is that they're probably
pretty good at preventing outages so we
usually hear about the the ones that
aren't prevented we don't hear about all
of the outages that were prevented which
happens every day and so again like if
you were to look at those articles that
you've said by Gmail and an AWS you know
up until the second those happened they
were pretty sure that they were
preventing them and so there's an ax
some of surprise that is inherent in
almost every no full stop every outage
because if you had predicted it and you
you prevented it then it wouldn't have
happened so I wouldn't I guess I would
say is that all of the things that go
into making the site run at all are all
of the thing
that help prevent outages it's a weird
semantic thing that I think it's easy to
skip over I could tell you a little bit
about well you know make sure you have
more than one server make sure you have
you know some redundant paths from this
service to that service or I could tell
you all of those things but those are
just common behaviors common maybe
design patterns and I don't know that's
that's all quite interesting but it's I
think it's straightforward it can't
really be construed as advice other than
you know carry a spare charger when
you're carrying your phone you know if
you're gonna be away from an outlet so I
feel like sorry to flip your question
around and I recognize I'm rambling a
little bit but in software one of the
things that concerns us so much is
designing to prevent failure and I think
that's absolutely a reasonable thing
it's never those things that bring about
outages almost never because we do the
things that we think we need to do what
interests me are the things and this was
actually a part of the research question
in my master's thesis which is when our
preventative designs fail us what then
right what are the things that happen in
an organization or technically with
software when the unexpected happens
your serum scene yeah that the planning
to avoid failure it is largely
successful because many systems do stay
up most of the time and had the planning
not been done there things would have
been much worse why is it not so simple
as we think of all the things that can
go wrong we planned for them and we have
a plan in place for each thing and we're
done why is it not that simple well
that's a good question I think that well
one way we could think about it is that
because of software and because we've
gotten pretty good at soft
where I guess that's debatable because
we've found new avenues of enabling
businesses our competitive advantages
through software that also brings new
opportunities for it to surprise us
right because these aren't these aren't
simple systems that we're building and
the opportunity for unintended
consequences becomes a lot greater and
it's not because the components don't
have a lot of eyeballs and and-and-and
and critical thinking around them all of
the sort of expected things are thought
of and certainly sort of prepared for
but there's always those things that
aren't expected that are beyond our
control the Internet is an open system
and so so I would say that software
reflects influences that we can't
predict yeah so let me follow up on this
for any system there are things which
are exogenous to your system there's
what you define as the boundary of your
system but you're using other things
whether it's hardware that a cloud
provider provides for you somebody
else's DNS our our outages often due to
these dependencies on things we don't
control and can we plan defensively
around services we consume but don't own
I mean I think the answer is yes to that
last question and that's already the
case so again it's about what we can
imagine it's not like well we can
imagine this but we can't come up with a
way that's economically viable or even
technically viable to guard against it I
think there's there are lots of pretty
common ways again just like you said you
can use a second DNS provider you could
use a third you could do things like
force feedback loops between CD ends or
moving in distributed database systems
you can you know change the number of of
replicas you have and there's lots of
dials and knobs but
I think that we have to accept that our
imagination is what drives us to build
those knobs and levers and reaching for
them when we need to is always gonna be
a matter of judgment and so so I guess
this is a long way of saying that yes
there's obviously a limit to
preventative design always and in fact I
might even argue that the reason why
things work as well as they do is
certainly partly because we build
redundancy and hot-hot fail overs and
things that can gracefully degrade all
of that but they still have operators
right whether the operator is a human
pressing a button or running command or
the human is imbuing their judgment into
some sort of quote-unquote self-healing
right turning up instances on ec2 is a
good example of that
you know we build in heuristics for auto
scaling you say oh well when this this
criteria and this criteria is met then
launch new instances and when just like
a thermostat in your house really and
when it goes down then turn them down
and that sort of thing so there's still
sort of judgment in there but I don't
know we still seem to get surprised so
the thing that interests me the most is
how do we behave we can talk all day
about how we behave in designing for
that those failure scenarios and
exercising our imagination and
anticipation skills I think that's great
and it's actually the I think it's the
topic of software engineering books and
and and and material for a couple of
decades
what isn't entirely understood is what
the hell we do when all of that doesn't
play out as our imagination so I think
that to address your exogenous
you know I think that that's inherent at
least on software that that sits in an
open system like the internet you can't
have users coming to your website and
have a objective deterministic idea of
exactly who they are and exactly what
they're going to be doing so it's can
either be a depressing outlook which his
failures gonna happen there's nothing
you can do about it and get used to it
that's a pretty dark way of thinking but
another way of saying is the opportunity
for failure is omnipresent and to quote
Richard Cooke who has a lot to say on
this topic which should surprise us is
not that our systems go down what you
surprised us is that they work at all
and that they and they work at all
because of people not just because of
software because we have to make active
effort yeah we should we sure did get
philosophical real quickly didn't we
yeah you're making it's pretty clear
there is a limit to how much we can plan
successfully to avoid failure and
planning twice as hard may not bring the
number of failures down by twice as much
there's a point where we need to think
about how we're going to respond when
failures do occur yes should we be
designing more to avoid failure or to
make systems fixable and recoverable I
think you're spot-on
I think I absolutely agree with the
letter there's a great phrase Eric
Holder Naugle says when talking in along
the lines of what the resilience
engineering lines of thought what-ho
Naugle says is developing a constant
sense of unease I like to say constant
sense of an ease rather than paranoia
but that constant sense of unease brings
you to think about you know more like
building and this is a often used
analogy more like designing and building
a Jeep
versus designing and building you know a
rolls-royce you know I don't know how it
is these days but a jeep used to come
with a set of tools and the designers of
a jeep it would show up with a full-size
spare tire and it would come with a set
of tools and that's probably largely
because Jeep knew their drivers and to
knew that they were gonna drive those
jeeps in not perfectly ideal conditions
so they expected that the cars gonna
break down and some or it's gonna need
some repair in some sort of way and so
they designed for that and that's where
this notion of designing for time to
respond and time to detect versus time
between failures are optimizing time
between failures give us some examples
of design to use or design patterns that
are aimed at time to fix well there's a
couple of different examples that come
to mind if you think about schema design
database schema design you know a
traditional though that's I wouldn't say
it's traditional these days but a
traditional way of thinking about
database design is through normalization
I'll store the data in one particular
way and what I'll do is I will
manipulate queries around it to get the
answers that I'm looking for well so I
think anybody who's ever built a
infrastructure at scale knows that
normalization is actually not at all the
route to go and there's sort of limits
to that especially when you're talking
about high volumes of queries and so
deep normalization which is I'm just
gonna store the data in multiple
different ways generally speaking on a
store it the way I expect to query it
even if it's even if it means spreading
duplicates of the data everywhere the
side effect of that is you know primary
key lookups in a database is really easy
to think about you don't have to draw a
picture in your mind like Oh what is
this join doing and what is this really
complicated query doing you can just say
select star from blah and where the
schema design itself makes it easier to
think about
the picture that you have in your mind
looks look simpler than something where
you've got to have some weird you know
OmniGraffle diagram in your mind when
you have to troubleshoot or diagnose or
debug something so another example and
it's pretty common now but whose
shocking how long it wasn't common is
that in these systems where we're
collecting telemetry sensor data or
metrics or whatever in systems like in
flux or graphite or whatever insert
favorite time series database here to
put interesting events draw infinite
vertical line on an interesting event
that may or may not have anything to do
with the metric you're looking at
inherently but is used to aid diagnosis
making it easier to make sense when
things aren't going you know you could
at least generate a hypothesis ooh did
did we change something at this time can
you think of a failure or incident you
were involved with where I took longer
to recover because you hadn't done
something that would have made your life
easier yes there are a lot of examples
there this was a story from a very very
long time ago at Etsy where we were
working on some pretty complicated
things to detect from weak signals
detect fraud and so we're requests come
from at what cadence do they come from
are they a bot is there something about
the traffic that makes it look like a
really human
and there's IP addresses their subnets
there's networks is it coming from a
data center is that coming from a home
IP you know that sort of thing and
because we built the tools to assume to
assume a lot about how primary the IP
address of a request really was as you
know central to whether or not it was
fraudulent or a fraudulent request or
not
well to cut this story short we banned
our own office IP address because it
tripped a number of different things and
so of course what does that mean it
means that people from inside the office
couldn't even diagnose why things
weren't working you say they're saying
so there's something sort of we fired
that gun back at us there are a number
of different things and it's a there's a
such a conundrum there's a belief and
it's so seductive there's a belief
especially in the wake of an incident or
while you're developing new code and
you're not entirely sure you're not
entirely certain about its behavior it's
so easy to collect time-series metrics
these days you're literally only one
line of code from getting really
complicated analytics around basically
any event you want at almost any time
resolution also the upside of that is
you can make a graph or something that
you can use to diagnose how your systems
are working so easily that we can have
millions and millions of them many
organizations do at all layers of the
stack from like Ethernet all the way up
to like something like you know searches
on Etsy some sort of like complicated
sort of business function and how ironic
is it that it's easy to collect all
those metrics and the more metrics you
have the harder it is to navigate
through them and so what do we find in a
lot of post-mortem debriefings is that
is not that oh we weren't graphing
something that we should have graphed
that's almost never the case we almost
always find a graph that would have
helped us during the time the data was
available it hadn't been observed right
so next thing you know no we got to
build a search engine for our graphs do
you see what I'm saying so there's these
unintended consequences I think that can
show up we ended up building something
and that we're kind of iterating on now
we had open sourced a project called
kale some time ago and it was sort of
the rough gist of it was okay I've got
this graph in
looks it was to help a diagnosis I've
got this graph it does this weird thing
this graph tells me something about a
symptom but I want to know more about it
so show me more graphs like this and it
was it was helpful were kind of
iterating on it now it wasn't
I think the impetus was that it would
really help it helped a little bit but
not a lot but yeah I think in the end
sometimes you need to build controls
knobs levers that seem kind of crazy to
build cuz you can't imagine a world
where you would need to do it but it
almost always turns out to be useful
searching for a new job is stressful and
scary then you go through the interview
process only to find the salary offer or
company culture doesn't match what
you're looking for hired comm is the
world's most intelligent talent matching
platform for engineering we make your
job search faster and stress-free after
completing the application top employers
apply to hire you you receive
personalized interview requests and
upfront salary information your
dedicated advocate will assist you
providing career coaching to help you
with potential employers hired comm
hides your profile from current and past
employers to respect your privacy the
best part it's always free today's se
radio listeners can earn a $2,000 hiring
bonus by signing up at hire comm / se
radio find your next chapter of hired
comm / se way
[Music]
you mentioned several times that these
systems we built humans are a part of
the system what is the role of human
error or human behavior in causing
outages I think I feel pretty strongly
about this which is that I actually
don't believe in human error I don't
believe it as a useful concept I
certainly can call almost anything an
error or a mistake definitely in
hindsight I just don't think it's useful
it doesn't tell us anything
so therefore if it doesn't tell us
anything I don't think it's useful to
use it as a cause and that's for a
number of different reasons mostly
because the term itself draws a box
around a person and not about the
context that the person found themselves
in and so you know where does design fit
with that I can make a website and
unfortunately lots of websites will do
this not on purpose
where it's really hard for you to find
the submit button or like the thing the
piece of user interaction if I can make
it hard for you to do the right thing
then when you do the wrong thing how
much of that is you versus how much of
that is my design and my intent for you
to do you see what I'm saying this idea
that people are doing what they think is
the right thing given the information
they have and they may be under a lot of
stress at the moment because their
employer is losing $1,000 a second and
you you have to understand what they did
and maybe there weren't any run books
and no one had told them crucial
information you have to take all of that
into account is that where you're going
yes absolutely
and I mean that is what you've
effectively described there is what's
known as the local rationality principle
which is exactly that people do what
makes sense to them at the time given
their goals their familiarity with this
scenario and
times it's not just time pressure of
course I don't know anybody who's not
under time pressure but it's also about
like how confident they are with tools
how confident they are with the scenario
that they're in and when I talk with
people on this particular topic
one of the things I generally do is I
ask people to raise their hand if they
feel really confident in using email of
course I get a roomful of hands and then
I say how many of you have more than a
decade and would say say that you're
basically an expert that email and most
people raise their hand and then I say
keep your hands up if you've ever sent
an email to somebody you didn't intend
to or if you replied all to a mailing
list you didn't intend to
and almost everybody keeps their hands
up in which case I said well are you an
expert or not and the fact of the matter
is it's too easy in email no matter how
much experience you have to make that
mistake and so if I want to get at that
well maybe I could get at that story if
I make it about you and you're not
paying attention or the mistake that you
made well I'm gonna miss out because
somebody else is gonna make a similar
mistake
but if I were to say well maybe we could
look at the algorithm that does
autocomplete on the to field of your
email client we could talk you know we
could we could think about that
as a design effort but yeah you're
exactly
you're exactly nailing it that is
generally my perspective and it's on its
it fortunately it's a growing
perspective that human error
is it's just simply not useful I think
that it's at one point in the world of
of safety and complex systems that we
may have thought it was useful it just
it's just not you mentioned earlier dr.
Richard cook we're gonna link to that
article in the show notes he says that
most of these problems do not have a
root cause and the search for the root
cause is harmful do you agree with dr.
cook on that and you're not in her
listeners can't see that so why why is
he right about that
well because cause is something that we
will convince ourselves of and I've
always been looking for
succinct ways of getting this concept
across and there's there's two one is a
story and the other is sort of a
statement and neither of them are
original or mine and I've talked with
Richard about them we don't use some
different part of our brain to make
mistakes then we do when we're
successful right it's the same brain we
do the same things and in fact we can do
one thing one day and do the exact same
thing the next day and the second time
we do it it might end up in a mistake
even though we we had all of the same
inputs and so that's called the
principle of equivalence right which is
that success and failure comes from the
same place so if you were to say that
finding the root cause of a failure
would be logically speaking similar to
saying there is a root cause of success
and I yet to find somebody who could
tell me definitively that there is a
root cause of what makes them success
that's that's concrete the so that's
sort of one way of thinking about it the
other way I'm gonna probably screw this
up there's a great book came out in the
I wanted to say in the 60s it was called
thinking by machines this was during the
times of maybe even earlier than sixties
during the times of cybernetics and
there's a there's a chapter that really
got at this this idea of the idea that
cause and effect have like a domino
effect and the example they say is you
know if you if you take a metal bar and
you put it into like a hot like oven
right the bar will expand or depending
on the material of the bar the like the
metal bar will sort of expand so then
you could say well what's the cause of
that expansion well on the one hand you
could say it was because of the
existence of the oven which is not wrong
the other is that you could say well
it's the heat in the oven and that also
wouldn't be wrong and then you could
also say it's about the heat the
temperature differential between before
you put it in the oven and when it was
in the oven which is also true and also
there's also other things that make it
such that create the conditions all of
which are necessary but only jointly
sufficient to cause the bar to lengthen
much in the same way I could say that
the cause of an outage is a person
running the wrong command on the wrong
server
are they here's a perfect example they
shut down the wrong server they shut
down the server that was in production
not taken out of production
perdón i could do that i can also
construct a story where the run book or
the procedure that the the engineer was
using hasn't been kept up to date and
they followed it perfectly from their
internal wiki
right I generally ask teams of engineers
raise your hand if you can find a wiki a
wiki page that has outdated information
in it in fact if you were to follow a
procedure top to bottom exactly how it's
written you're gonna have a bad day they
everyone raises their hand right so I
can also tell a story about how the the
the engineer wasn't trained or that they
weren't paying attention it's about
where we draw a line to say what are the
things that we will consider right and
so don't think of anything that give a
any think of a DDoS attack right let me
stop you here and you summarize what I
think you're going with this is and I'm
tying together things you've said at
different points these systems are
complex they have a lot of parts the
parts interact in order to have a
failure we are pretty good at thinking
of preventing failures when one thing
happens so generally if we've done our
jobs if failure occurs because multiple
things happened and none of those things
could be said to be the root cause
because if any one of those things by
itself that happened probably we have
enough layers of protection that we're
good now is that a fair summary of what
you've been saying yes that's exactly
right we talked some about prevention we
talked about responding and fixing
you've also mentioned post-mortem the
idea of a learning from things that went
wrong how can we best learn from these
experiences I think there's a couple of
things that might not be readily
apparent it's quite common to have a
post-mortem meeting or a debriefing
I think that there are multiple goals of
having such a discussion or meeting or a
process and I think one of the most
successful ways of doing it is
ironically not solely focusing on
what was special about the event you're
talking about let me tell you a little
let me give you a little bit of
background let me back up in some of the
most successful and I mean really
valuable
post-mortem do briefings that I've been
a part of is when the facilitator or or
somebody in the group usually these are
sort of group discussions maybe we could
you just briefly say what is a
post-mortem oh sure sure the term
post-mortem in a software sense is
generally a a meeting or discussion or
sometimes it's referred it's referring
to a process it's effectively part
either a debriefing or a discussion that
is typically attended by a group and and
the the ideal scenario is that you are
discussing an event and actions and
decisions that surround a sort of a time
boxed event in the hopes that you'll
that through dialogue and discussion
you'll learn something in order to to
age prevention in the future great I
interrupted you a moment ago you were
starting to talk about one of the most
useful experiences you've had in a
post-mortem let's go back to that I
think a traditional way of thinking
about a post-mortem is do you you know
you lay out a timeline and you you zoom
straight in and find the the the idea
would be to go and find the part that
broke whether that part is a component
or a command that that that was run at
the wrong time or or or something it's a
narrowing and we almost never learn much
about that other than you know like we
mentioned before well you always when
you when you narrow like that you'll
find
somebody who did something wrong
basically and if you were to take a
different approach and this is the
approach that I that I found to be
hugely beneficial at Etsy is and in
other organizations as well which is to
use the event as really just an anchor
for you to ask about how things normally
go
and so when we hear it when in a
debriefing you'll say all right so let's
start at the beginning before this
outage happened you know Lisa what was
going on what were you doing what you
know and Lisa will tell you well I had
to replace this you know I had to
restore this back up for this thing and
whatever and she'll go on till a story
and if you ask probing questions about
how she normally does her work
remember outages like we said for the
very beginning outages are surprises and
a surprise is a contrast between the way
reality unfolded and how you thought it
was going to unfold right which means
that if you don't talk about how things
normally go you're not gonna hear about
well I ran this command and oh and what
did you expect to happen well I expected
that it was gonna restore the database
right so and so when you hear that
that's exactly what you were getting it
which is we are trying to find out what
actions and decisions made sense for
people what made it make sense for them
because what we always find our people
will tell you well I do this and I do
that but when you know I do this a
hundred times a month and sometimes
they'll they'll say yeah well they'll
want to zoom straight in to that one
time that they did this no no I want you
to tell me what you normally do because
that'll help us explain how you found
yourself in this situation and so so
that's why it's this weird thing you're
in the room because of a failure
but the greatest learning comes from
when people tell you about how they
normally succeed doing that stuff I'm
the person in this meeting I tell you I
back this file up then I expect that I
see the file is there on the disk or in
the folder but it wasn't this time what
are you going to learn from that or what
is actionable that will add some value
to your organization in the future that
will come from that
so in our little hypothetical scenario
ideally we're not going to get just this
one story from you we're gonna get
stories from as many perspectives as
possible right and in that case I'd you
know a network engineer says oh well was
what it was Moses Thursday morning yeah
well every Thursday morning at 10:00 you
know we unmount
all of the NFS mounts to do some like
whatever insert you know network
maintenance thing here and it takes for
about three minutes and generally it and
we just remount everything and that's
what happened well when do you usually
do this oh I only I usually do it on
Wednesday night but you know I was sick
that day so I just figured I'd do it the
next morning so that's we were we would
learn you know a scenario this
hypothetical is really constructed but
you you get what I'm saying yeah and
then what we could say is oh hey if
you're gonna unmount NFS you know put
something in message of the day or you
know like make it so that you you can't
actually put files there you know I'm
gonna change the subject a bit to talk
about testing we've talked a lot about
planning and that might take the form or
of thinking what if this happens
instance goes away DNS goes down what is
the role of testing in preventing
failures and can we build a test
environment can we test enough there to
find out how it's really going to act in
production well there's a couple
questions in there I'll take the last
one because it's the easiest no
remember I will have to say a really
smart guy to follow on Twitter about
this topic is Noah Sussman
she's twerk at Etsy some some years ago
and what Noah does is is is is point out
almost on a daily basis that there are
always things that we don't even know to
test for and that's really the simple
answer to you know that's really the
simple explanation about what y know so
there's not a scenario where you can
construct a perfect set of testing now
that does not mean that testing and the
activity of writing testing isn't hugely
valuable I think there's something that
is a source of a source of strength I
would say certainly a source of a source
of learning in an organization is the
act of writing tests themselves just
because the test isn't gonna capture all
of the myriad things that is gonna
happen in production one thing that you
can do is say and be really upfront this
is exactly what this test does it does
nothing more than this you know and
really flesh out the description in
comments and other sorts of
documentation this is exactly what it
does so therefore you can feel confident
about it what it doesn't do
do you see what I'm saying here's where
the limits of this test are the other
thing that I think is sometimes skipped
over in an effort to test all of the
things or provide you know perfect
confidence which like I said is
impossible is that tests much like all
software is really just the encoded
intentions it's a little bit like the
encoded imagination of the engineer one
developer writes a unit test it's
implicitly represents what that
developer does not feel confident about
absent the test which is a really great
signal it gives you some insight you can
make some inferences about what's going
on up in there you know their their
mental model which I think is really
really valuable something you've written
about John and we'll link to this in the
show notes is concept of fault injection
in production explain what that is and
why you are an advocate yeah and there's
a couple of were different ways of
thinking about it article I had written
the four ACM some years ago is really
just a specific version or specific case
of what Netflix ended up calling chaos
monkey and really a what that means is
constructing a test in production
purposefully in production where you are
injecting some sort of fault and I mean
an actual fault so examples that we've
done in the past are alright well you
know a month from now we've got this
these new set of databases and we want
to write the code so that so that it it
doesn't you know go all wonky when the
database isn't there so this is what
we're gonna do we're gonna on the 31st
of the month we're gonna you know go to
the data center or we're gonna log into
AWS and we're just gonna nuke like we're
either we'll either just yank the power
cables from the box while it's running
or we'll just completely nuke the
instance in the case of AWS to be clear
on this you're talking about doing this
on your live production system that your
business runs on correct correct
the reason why you do that and you say
that I am going to do this in the future
now this is a little bit different than
the way Netflix goes with chaos monkey
and chaos monkey has and and they're the
other forms of their sort of simian army
software they might choose to do things
randomly but conceptually it's still
it's still the same which is we're
planning on doing this what do we need
to do to make our systems not care that
this happens and what it does is
exercise new kinds of imagination and
knowing that it will actually happen in
real life means that you're playing
without a net and that can be really
uncomfortable but the fact is you're
either doing it while you're there and
watching it or you're do or it's or it
can happen while you're not watching and
you're not prepping for it
you're thinking we have a standby or a
cluster or failover in theory if the one
goes away the other one should take over
mm-hmm let's be sure that it really
works that way
because we don't want to find out to the
contrary at 3:00 a.m. on Thursday
morning exactly exactly and there I have
to say is that once you and as a leader
in the organization once you make it
safe for people to start exercising this
part of their anticipation and building
this anticipation skills and like um it
can it can be really fun you know to
think of all the horrible things that
you can do just software and hardware
and and aim at making these Z's tonight
and make no mistake they are contrived
that doesn't mean that you're gonna come
up with something that's exactly gonna
happen like that in the future it can be
really fun to think about how can I make
it so that if my binary files of my
database get totally corrupted how do I
make that how do I make it so I don't
have to care or I don't have to freak
out when that happens and it can be fun
you sound like really good things to
know and to know that you can deal with
them I am gonna guess here you wouldn't
do these on production if you thought
you could do an adequate simulation of
this on a staging system or test system
that you would build offline yeah why
why do you have to do this in production
well I just I've yet to see and maybe
this is I mean I've only been doing this
for about 20 years so I probably maybe I
don't have enough experience but I have
yet to meet a staging environment that
is perfectly and I mean truly and
perfectly with with no doubt a mirror of
production that that is seeing the
diversity of
traffic the diversity of temperature of
interconnections and and and work as as
production so and usually what I say is
look if you're not if you're if you're
not comfortable enough to do it on
production it just means you're not done
yet
one more testing question then we'll
wrap up my view is I see a lot of tools
frameworks best practices books
conferences blog posts about how to test
the code which in the context we're
talking about you could call that a
simple system because the code all runs
inside a runtime that's just one thing
whereas a lot of these failures come
about because of the interaction of
different parts or you have
infrastructure changes which in theory
you should retest everything when you
change a piece of infrastructure and
make sure that all it has a used to pass
is it fair to say that the discipline
and the domain around testing
infrastructure and systems is less
advanced than around testing code hmm I
don't know if I would be so strong if
this was five or six years ago maybe I
might say that I think that I think that
the state of the art of configuration
management that's one example cluster
management orchestration I think that
the state of the art there has reached a
point where there is you know I don't
know I'm probably not the right person
to coin something like this but there
are there are equivalents of what you
would otherwise call unit tests or
functional tests but for infrastructure
or that is to say multiple layers of the
stack I think that the amount of
manipulation there is to say
infrastructure so
think about load balancers and internal
DNS and routing and distributed
databases all of the things that
surround thick sorted The Container
ecosystem and all of the orchestrating
things like kubernetes have turned a
majority of up like a lot of those other
things that had always been seen as
separate from the code into code right
that this was the promise that Adam
Jacob and Luke anis and Andrew Schaeffer
this is the promise that you could treat
infrastructure as code in which case you
could theoretically do things that you
otherwise previously wouldn't have been
able to do and I think that that's
actually been going on for a number of
years and there's there's lots of folks
who have been thinking about this
problem and making a lot of progress the
one caveat that I would say there and
this maybe loops back a little bit to
the very beginning which is and yet we
will still be surprised that's a great
place to end to close out John where can
people find you on the Internet
well I have a blog at kitchen soap.com
don't ask me about the name it's just
two words that was really easy to
pronounce and people would remember and
my hope is to write a lot more thereon
in 2017 that I have in the past this the
CTO gig here has been pretty busy but
that's where you can find me and listen
to my ramblings thank you so much and
thank you for speaking with software
engineering radio thank you for software
engineering radio this has been Robert
Bluman
[Music]
thanks for listening to se Radio an
educational program brought to you by I
Triple E software magazine for more
information about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at SE -
radio net to provide feedback you can
write comments on each episode on the
website or write a review on itunes
mention a message us on Twitter at se
radio or search for the software
engineering radio group on LinkedIn
Google+ or Facebook you can also email
us at team at se - radio net this and
all other episodes of SU radio is
licensed under the creative commons
two-point-five license thanks again for
your support
you
[Music]